<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<issue id="0002" status="review">
  <title>Isolate mise-backed tools behind bubblewrap in scrubs guests</title>
  <user-story>
    <as-a>scrubs VM user with clean guest-local credentials</as-a>
    <i-want>mise-backed tools and package-manager workloads to run inside a constrained bubblewrap boundary by default</i-want>
    <so-that>dirty JavaScript and Rust workflows can use project tooling without gaining ambient access to clean credentials, unrelated files, or arbitrary clean executables</so-that>
  </user-story>
  <premise>
    The working model is: clean space is the Nix store plus guest-local
    credential-bearing configuration, while dirty space is the `mise` store
    and the developer tooling reached through it. Clean space may launch dirty
    tools, but dirty tools should not gain ambient access to clean
    credentials, unrelated files, or arbitrary clean executables.

    The current scrubs guest exposes `mise` broadly in interactive and
    non-interactive shells, so `node`, `bun`, `cargo`, and related tools are
    ambiently available in clean space. We want to invert that model. The
    likely shape is a proxy-shim layer that preserves normal command names and
    completions while resolving the real `mise` target and executing it inside
    a bubblewrap sandbox with a synthetic home, limited writable paths, no
    real `gh` or `codex` credentials, and only a curated helper-tool subset
    from clean space. `git` is a special case: some dirty workflows need it,
    but it should run there with fake or stripped credentials rather than
    inheriting the clean identity.
  </premise>
  <acceptance-criteria>
    <criterion>Clean interactive shells no longer ambiently activate `mise`, and direct use of known dirty commands fails closed unless it goes through the scrubs launcher.</criterion>
    <criterion>A proxy-shim or equivalent dispatcher preserves normal command names such as `node`, `pnpm`, `bun`, and `cargo` while executing the real `mise`-managed tool inside bubblewrap.</criterion>
    <criterion>Dirty execution receives a synthetic home plus only the project working tree, `/tmp`, and other explicitly approved writable paths.</criterion>
    <criterion>Dirty execution cannot read the real guest credential stores for `gh`, `codex`, SSH, or other clean-space identities.</criterion>
    <criterion>Dirty execution can reach only a curated helper-tool subset from clean space rather than the full clean profile.</criterion>
    <criterion>At least one workflow that shells out to `git` works in dirty space with fake or stripped credentials and without access to the clean identity.</criterion>
    <criterion>The default user experience still supports ordinary command entry and completions for the wrapped tools without requiring users to learn alternate command names.</criterion>
  </acceptance-criteria>
  <review-items>
    <item status="covered">
      The dirty guest habitat is now a first-class guest-wide sandbox
      definition rather than an implicit collection of shell-script decisions.
      The helper command basket, copied identity files, read-only ambient
      system facts, and `/proc` exposure now live in a declared artifact, and
      project shims may replace that artifact with a guest-specific sandbox
      definition when they need a different dirty-world view.
    </item>
    <item status="covered">
      The `wayforge` Bun regression established that the dirty habitat must be
      minimal but believable, not merely sparse. Validation covered the choice
      to expose `/proc`, `/sys`, `/etc/localtime`, and other low-sensitivity
      runtime facts so modern `mise` tooling can function without reopening the
      full clean environment.
    </item>
    <item status="covered">
      A re-bootstrap regression in the shell-startup path was introduced while
      this work was in flight, likely by this task or the Docker lifecycle work
      in `0001`. Interactive `limactl shell` sessions began crashing after a
      repeat bootstrap because scrubs-managed `~/.bashrc` files were being
      recopied into `~/.bashrc.pre-scrubs`, causing recursive sourcing. The
      missing `SCRUBS_BASHRC` marker and the migration path for already-broken
      guests have both been fixed, and repeat bootstrap validation restored
      interactive shell access on the same guest across successive bootstraps.
    </item>
    <item status="open">
      Continue reviewing whether the declared guest-wide habitat is still
      narrow enough as more runtimes are exercised, especially when new tools
      require additional ambient Linux facts or helper commands.
    </item>
    <item status="open">
      Decide how dirty `git` should be provisioned, including fake identity,
      disabled credential helpers, and any narrowly scoped auth that specific
      tools may still require.
    </item>
    <item status="open">
      Validate the boundary with a red-team style probe that confirms dirty
      commands can see the project and approved scratch space but not real
      clean-space credential directories or unrelated files. This is now being
      broken out into a dedicated follow-on audit task so it can wait on the
      design of a purpose-built "virtual burglar" harness.
    </item>
  </review-items>
</issue>
