<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<issue id="0003" status="open">
  <title>Harden clean-space credential storage in scrubs guests</title>
  <user-story>
    <as-a>scrubs VM user with guest-local clean credentials</as-a>
    <i-want>clean-space tokens such as GitHub CLI and Codex credentials to avoid plaintext-at-rest storage by default</i-want>
    <so-that>the remaining clean-side blast radius is reduced even if dirty execution controls improve only incrementally</so-that>
  </user-story>
  <premise>
    The current scrubs model intentionally separates clean and dirty execution,
    but some clean-space credentials are still only as safe as their at-rest
    storage. Today, `gh auth login` in a scrubs guest reports that
    authentication credentials were saved in plain text, which is consistent
    with GitHub CLI behavior when no usable system credential store is
    available. The guest currently does not provision a secret-service style
    keyring or another clearly supported secure backend for `gh`, and the same
    broader question applies to other clean-space credentials such as Codex
    authentication.

    This means the bubblewrap boundary helps protect clean credentials from
    dirty execution, but the clean credentials themselves may still be stored
    more weakly than we want. Hardening this area should focus on how clean
    credentials persist at rest, whether plaintext fallback should be forbidden
    by policy, and whether scrubs should prefer ephemeral environment injection,
    a guest-local credential manager, or another explicit storage model.
  </premise>
  <acceptance-criteria>
    <criterion>Scrubs has an explicit policy for clean-space credential persistence, including whether plaintext storage is ever permitted.</criterion>
    <criterion>`gh auth login` in a scrubs guest no longer silently falls back to plaintext storage, either because a supported secure backend is available or because scrubs fails closed when secure storage is unavailable.</criterion>
    <criterion>The chosen storage model is documented for both GitHub CLI and Codex authentication, including where credentials live and how they are revoked or rotated.</criterion>
    <criterion>Dirty execution remains unable to read or invoke the resulting clean credential stores under the bubblewrap boundary.</criterion>
    <criterion>At least one validation path demonstrates the final behavior end to end, including the expected `gh auth status` or equivalent evidence of where credentials are stored.</criterion>
  </acceptance-criteria>
  <review-items>
    <item status="open">
      Decide whether scrubs should provision a guest-local credential store,
      forbid persistent CLI login and rely on ephemeral environment variables,
      or support multiple approved modes with a clear default.
    </item>
    <item status="open">
      Identify how Codex authentication is currently stored in guests and
      whether its persistence model should match GitHub CLI or be handled
      differently.
    </item>
    <item status="open">
      Decide whether clean-space git authentication should continue to rely on
      GitHub CLI integration, a git credential helper, SSH keys, or a separate
      scrubs-specific approach once credential storage is hardened.
    </item>
  </review-items>
</issue>
