<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<issue id="0004" status="open">
  <title>Red-team the dirty-runtime boundary against package-borne secret exfiltration</title>
  <user-story>
    <as-a>scrubs VM user relying on the clean/dirty split</as-a>
    <i-want>a purpose-built adversarial audit of dirty package execution paths</i-want>
    <so-that>I can measure whether npm and cargo supply-chain malware would actually fail to reach or exfiltrate the clean-space secrets we care about</so-that>
  </user-story>
  <premise>
    Scrubs now routes `mise`-backed tooling through a guest-wide bubblewrap
    habitat with explicit helper commands and ambient Linux facts. That gives
    us a meaningful defensive boundary, but our primary threat model is not a
    friendly compatibility smoke test. It is package-borne malware arriving
    through npm, pnpm, Bun, Cargo, or adjacent tooling and attempting to read
    or exfiltrate secrets from the guest.

    The right way to evaluate that boundary is not just ad hoc manual poking.
    We need a purpose-built "virtual burglar" harness that behaves like a dirty
    package with realistic exfiltration goals: enumerate accessible files,
    inspect environment and helper tools, attempt access to clean credential
    stores, try common subprocess pivots, and prove what can and cannot leave
    the sandbox over the network. That harness does not exist yet, so this task
    is intentionally blocked on designing it well.
  </premise>
  <acceptance-criteria>
    <criterion>Scrubs has a documented adversarial audit harness or equivalent repeatable test plan that models npm- and cargo-borne secret-exfiltration malware inside dirty execution.</criterion>
    <criterion>The audit explicitly targets the clean-space secrets and metadata that matter to the scrubs threat model, including GitHub CLI, Codex, SSH material, unrelated home-directory files, and other guest-local clean credentials.</criterion>
    <criterion>The audit captures both read-access attempts and exfiltration attempts, including what a dirty process can discover through environment variables, helper binaries, ambient Linux facts, network egress, and subprocess spawning.</criterion>
    <criterion>At least one validation run demonstrates what the harness can and cannot reach under the current sandbox policy, with concrete evidence that can be reviewed later.</criterion>
    <criterion>The resulting findings either confirm the current defensive posture against the primary threat model or produce concrete follow-on hardening issues.</criterion>
  </acceptance-criteria>
  <review-items>
    <item status="open">
      Design the "virtual burglar" harness so it is realistic enough to model
      hostile package behavior without itself becoming an unreviewable blob of
      ad hoc probes.
    </item>
    <item status="open">
      Decide how much of the harness should live as code in the repo versus a
      documented repeatable operator procedure, especially if some probes need
      intentionally malicious behavior.
    </item>
    <item status="open">
      Decide how the audit should account for network egress, since the primary
      threat model is not just secret readability but successful exfiltration.
    </item>
    <item status="open">
      Keep this task blocked until `0002` and `0003` are merged far enough that
      the harness would be auditing the intended baseline rather than a moving
      target.
    </item>
  </review-items>
</issue>
