<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<issue id="0006" status="open">
  <title>Explore porting notes and task files to Pug</title>
  <user-story>
    <as-a>maintainer working across Markdown notes and XML task files</as-a>
    <i-want>to evaluate whether those authoring formats should move to Pug or a Pug-centered source model</i-want>
    <so-that>the repo can use a more uniform, ergonomic authoring shape without giving up clarity, structure, or reviewability</so-that>
  </user-story>
  <premise>
    The repo currently keeps human-authored notes as Markdown documents and
    structured work items as XML issue files. That split is workable, but it
    means authoring conventions, tooling, and formatting differ between two
    adjacent kinds of project documentation. A Pug-centered approach might
    offer a more concise writing experience and a shared shape for both looser
    notes and more structured task records.

    This should begin as an exploration, not an assumed migration. Markdown
    remains highly readable in raw form, XML remains explicit and easy to
    validate structurally, and both are broadly tool-friendly. Any proposal to
    port either notes or task files to Pug needs to explain what becomes
    better, what becomes harder, and how diffs, editor ergonomics, formatting,
    and agent ingestion would change.

    With the likely exception of README-style files, the purpose of these
    notes is not primarily to render them into another presentation layer. The
    raw files themselves are the product: humans read them directly in editors
    and terminals, and agents ingest them as source material. That means a Pug
    proposal should be treated skeptically if it depends on a render step for
    ordinary use, weakens raw-file readability, or introduces tooling that
    makes the canonical text less accessible than today's Markdown and XML.
  </premise>
  <acceptance-criteria>
    <criterion>The repo has a written evaluation of Pug as a source format for both note-like documents and structured task records, including benefits, drawbacks, and non-goals.</criterion>
    <criterion>The evaluation compares at least three shapes: keep Markdown and XML as-is, use Pug only for one document class, or adopt a Pug-centered source model, while treating render-dependent workflows as a poor fit outside README-like exceptions.</criterion>
    <criterion>The exploration identifies how metadata, headings, lists, code blocks, and task-specific structured fields would be represented without losing important readability or validation properties.</criterion>
    <criterion>The work evaluates raw-file readability and agent-ingestion ergonomics as first-class requirements, including whether a maintainer can comfortably read and edit representative files without compiling or previewing them.</criterion>
    <criterion>The work includes a concrete proposal for how review ergonomics, formatting, and automation would function, including whether `dprint` can format the chosen source shape directly or would need new plugins, custom tooling, or an intentional gap.</criterion>
    <criterion>The exploration records whether Pug has solid syntax-highlighting and editing support in the editors we actually favor, and treats weak editor support as a meaningful strike against migration.</criterion>
    <criterion>If Pug looks viable, the task leaves behind a narrow pilot plan for one representative note file and one representative task file before any broad migration is attempted.</criterion>
  </acceptance-criteria>
  <review-items>
    <item status="open">
      Decide whether Pug would be a direct replacement format, an authoring
      source for canonical raw files, or merely a templating aid for selected
      structured documents where raw readability matters less.
    </item>
    <item status="open">
      Compare raw-file readability carefully, since these notes and task files
      are meant to be read directly by humans and ingested directly by agents.
    </item>
    <item status="open">
      Check formatter and editor support early, especially whether `dprint`
      can participate and whether favored editors offer dependable syntax
      highlighting and editing behavior for Pug.
    </item>
    <item status="open">
      Identify the smallest realistic pilot so the evaluation can test author
      experience, diff quality, automation burden, and ingestion ergonomics
      before touching the broader corpus.
    </item>
  </review-items>
</issue>
